<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter to a person of quality, occasioned by the burning of Sir John Presbyter, in the Deans Yard Westminster, Novemb. 5. 1681. To the L.B.R. D.W.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B25903</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99889169</idno>
  <idno type="VID">193688</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240903844</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1693</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide 816.m.2[37]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R233660</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99889169</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99889169e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B25903)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 193688)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; C27:4[55])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter to a person of quality, occasioned by the burning of Sir John Presbyter, in the Deans Yard Westminster, Novemb. 5. 1681. To the L.B.R. D.W.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([2] p.).   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681].</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dated and signed at end: "London Nov. 11. 1681. O.Q."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Presbyterianism --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Dissenters, Religious --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>John Pas </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:193688:1"/>
            <head>A LETTER TO A Person of Quality, Occasioned by the Burning of Sir John Presbyter, In the <hi>Deans</hi> Yard WESTMINSTER, <hi>Novemb.</hi> 5. 1681.</head>
            <head type="sub">To the L. B. R. D. W.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe eminent Character which you bear in the Church, and those personal Accomplishments, which, I have been informed, you are Master of, have formerly engaged me to a very great Reverence for your Lordship's Name, and Person. But that late scandalous Action in <hi>Deans-yard</hi> on the 5th. of <hi>November,</hi> which could never have been done without your Countenance, and Permission (as every one must conclude, who knows any thing of your Relation to that Society) hath now given me (as well as many others) too just an occasion of entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing different Sentiments concerning you, from what I had hitherto re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd. However, my former Respects have now engaged me to send your Lordship these few lines, and thereby to acquaint you with those Censures, which are generally past upon that Action. I hope you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Lordship will peruse them without <hi>Peevishness</hi> and <hi>Passion;</hi> since it is a happiness, which few great Men enjoy; to be faithfully enform'd of that Judgment, which the World makes concerning them.</p>
            <p>Briefly then, <hi>My Lord,</hi> all sober persons of all perswasions were great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly surpriz'd with regret, and grief, to read so scurrilous a story trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phantly proclaim'd to the World by <hi>Tompson</hi> in his <hi>Tuesdays Intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence,</hi> and to find upon Enquiry so little of his wonted forgery in that Relation. Especially, since it was acted on <hi>that day</hi> which is by <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> set apart for the commemoration of our great Deliverance from a <hi>Popish</hi> Conspiracy; and at <hi>such</hi> a <hi>juncture</hi> too of time; when we are <hi>All</hi> equally in danger of becoming a prey to those merciless Enemies, who will not only <hi>wish</hi> (as <hi>Tompson</hi> tells us <hi>your Scholars</hi> did) <hi>that the Person of him who was represented, and all his followers were burnt like that Image,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:193688:2"/>but <hi>really effect</hi> it, when they have an Opportunity; and that not only upon <hi>one</hi> party, but on <hi>all,</hi> who will not readily submit themselves to that Antichristian Yoke, and Tyranny. It is said hereupon,</p>
            <p>That your Lordship by encouraging this, hath confuted that opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of your <hi>Moderation</hi> towards <hi>Dissenters,</hi> which was so commonly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain'd and believ'd; and that there is too much cause to fear, if you still retain any thing of <hi>Temper,</hi> the <hi>Papists</hi> are the <hi>principal</hi> objects of it.</p>
            <p>That we may now perceive the great Prudence of our late <hi>Parliament</hi> in repealing the Statute <hi>De Haeretico Comburendo,</hi> and abridging the Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchy of that Exorbitant power they thereby enjoy'd over such, as they pleas'd to brand with the odious Name of <hi>Heretick;</hi> since even <hi>one</hi> of our <hi>Bishops</hi> hath in so publick a manner express'd his willingness to have it executed on his <hi>Fellow-Protestants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That it is to be fear'd, a late Popish Pamphlet entituled <hi>The Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the English Catholicks</hi> hath too just ground to speak with so much respect of <hi>your Lordship,</hi> while in the mean time it accounts the Pious and Learned <hi>Bishop</hi> of <hi>Lincoln</hi> to be <hi>scarce a Christian.</hi> And,</p>
            <p>That doubtless your Lordship expects some extraordinary Reward under a <hi>Popish Successor,</hi> for manifesting already so <hi>Fiery</hi> a zeal against those whom that Party esteem (if not their <hi>ONLY,</hi> yet) their <hi>great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est</hi> Enemies.</p>
            <p>That by thus burning the <hi>Presbyteri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> in <hi>Essig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e</hi> you seem to reproach His Majesties great Kindness, and to condemn many worthy Persons charity to the poore distressed <hi>French</hi> Protestants, who are all of <hi>that</hi> perswasion, and therefore, according to the Doctrine taught in <hi>your</hi> School, deserve rather to be burnt, then reliev'd.</p>
            <p>That if any Man can think it worth his pains to enquire into the lives of many of the <hi>Actors</hi> in that <hi>spiteful Scene,</hi> he may thence too justly conclude (as one did of the Christians in <hi>Nero's</hi> time) <hi>that they must cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly be very good Men, who are so mortally hated by Persons of such profli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate Conversations.</hi> But however,</p>
            <p>That the <hi>Dissenters</hi> are not conscious to themselves of any Crimes, that might deserve so severe a treatment, unless it be that <hi>one</hi> of dissenting from the Established Church in things not necessary to salvation; which tho it be an <hi>unpardonable</hi> sin with some sorts of men, yet will assured<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prove more <hi>Venial</hi> with the Almighty hereafter, then the <hi>Excessive Drinkings,</hi> Pledging of <hi>Scandalous Healths,</hi> and <hi>Preposterous unnatural Loves</hi> of <hi>some,</hi> who account every expression of their malice against <hi>them,</hi> to be an acceptable piece of service to God, and <hi>an eminent Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal of Loyalty</hi> to their Earthly Soveraign.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>London Nov.</hi> 11. 1681.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>O. Q.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>